From conditions, we move to loops, technically,
iterations, and the different types of loops used
in Python and many other programming languages.
When using a loop, the first determination is:
should the loop run a set number of times,
or should the loop run until a condition is
true or false? Here is a case in point: this
221-while code file. A person playing a game
starts with a score of 0. Every time the player
does something good, 10 points are awarded. The
task that needs to be done to get the points is
not important here. We want the player to get a
message every 10 points updating the score, and
then, when 100 points are reached, we want the
player to see a congratulatory message. Loops
that run while conditions are true or false are
known as while loops. I will follow this code
example to show the facets of a while loop and
when one is used. Line 4 shows a while keyword
with a condition: while the score is less than
100. As with an if statement, the while clause
ends with a colon. Lines 5 and 6 are indented,
so they are part of the while loop. Line 5 has
a print statement printing a message containing
the score. Yes, you can use plus signs or commas
as concatenating symbols in Python. Commas work
better with data of different types, like these
two strings with an integer in between. And commas
put automatic spaces in between strings of text.
I will run this code, and we see the code loop
through and add 10 points. Then, when the score
reaches 100, the loop ends, and we see the last
print statement from line 8. There are two aspects
of conditional loops to be careful about. First,
ensure you have the correct comparison operator
when setting a condition. To illustrate this
point, I will change the operator on line 4 from
a less than symbol to less than or equal to. When
rerunning the code, the only change we see in
the output is that we get a message for having
100 points. Neither situation is right or wrong,
but notice that operators can control output,
so think through what you want the code to do
and set your operators accordingly so that an
app can behave as expected. The other point of
awareness for conditional loops is to ensure
the loop stops running at some point. If we were
to change the score increase to 0, for example,
and rerun the code, the code would be stuck in
an endless loop because the while clause would
never be reached. At this point, the only way
to stop running the app is by selecting Ctrl+C
on the keyboard or waiting for the app to crash
from running out of memory. For these reasons,
we want to ensure we know what we want a
conditional loop to do before building the code
for the loop so that the loop runs efficiently
and produces the desired results within an app.